They'll never get caught. They're on a mission from God.
The Blues Brothers is a music, comedy, action film directed by John Landis.
Jake Blues, just released from prison, puts his old band back together to save
the Catholic home where he and his brother Elwood were raised.
Elwood Blues, played by Dan Aykroyd.
'Joliet' Jake Blues, played by John Belushi.
Cleophus James, played by James Brown.
Curtis, played by Cab Calloway.
Ray, played by Ray Charles.
Mrs. Murphy, played by Aretha Franklin.
The Blues Brothers is a 1980 American musical action
comedy film directed by John Landis.
It stars John Belushi as "Joliet" Jake Blues and Dan Aykroyd as his brother Elwood, characters developed from
the recurring musical sketch "The Blues Brothers" on NBC's variety series Saturday Night Live.
The script is set in and around Chicago, Illinois, where it was
filmed, and the screenplay is by Aykroyd and Landis.
It features musical numbers by singers James Brown, Cab Calloway,
Aretha Franklin, Ray Charles and John Lee Hooker.
It features non-musical supporting performances by
Carrie Fisher and Henry Gibson.
The story is a tale of redemption for paroled convict Jake and his brother Elwood, who set out on "a mission
from God" to prevent the foreclosure of the Roman Catholic orphanage in which they were raised.
To do so, they must reunite their rhythm and blues (R&B) band and organize a
performance to earn the $5,000 needed to pay the orphanage's property tax bill.
Along the way, they are targeted by a homicidal "mystery woman", neo-Nazis and a
country and western band—all while being relentlessly pursued by the police.
Universal Pictures, which won the bidding war for the film, was hoping to take advantage of Belushi's popularity in the wake of Saturday Night
Live, the film Animal House, and the Blues Brothers' musical success; it soon found itself unable to control production costs.
The start of filming was delayed when Aykroyd, who was new to film screenwriting, took six months to deliver a long and
unconventional script that Landis had to rewrite before production, which began without a final budget.
On location in Chicago, Belushi's partying and drug use caused lengthy and costly delays that, along with the
destructive car chases depicted onscreen, made the film one of the most expensive comedies ever produced.
Owing to concerns that the film would fail, its initial bookings were
less than half of those similar films normally received.
Released in the United States on June 20, 1980, it received mostly positive reviews from critics and grossed over $115
million in theaters worldwide before its release on home video, and has become a cult classic over the years.
A sequel, Blues Brothers 2000, was released in 1998.
In 2020, The Blues Brothers was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry
by the Library of Congress as "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of prison, chicago,
illinois, dancing, concert, country music.
The tone is lighthearted.